A Finding Aid to the John Opper Papers, 1926-2011, in the Archives of American Art AAA.oppejohn
Archives of American Art
John Opper papers
1926-2011
AAA.oppejohn
Archives of American Art
1.4 Linear feet
The papers of abstract painter and teacher John Opper measure 1.4 linear feet and are dated 1926-2011. The papers contain both professional and personal corespondence, including letters from immediate family. Biographical materials consist of essential data including passports, birth and death certificates, and curricula vitae. Personal business records relate to the artist's Bowery Street and Amagansett studios, and to art sales through the Grace Borgenicht Gallery. A scrapbook contains newspaper clippings. Additional clippings, group and solo exhibition catalogs and announcements documenting Opper's career, and galley sheets of a children's book illustrated by Opper are included among the printed material. Photographs are of Opper, his family, friends, and paintings. Digital photographs depict the artist and relatives and also include images of genealogical records. The collection also contains a few pen and ink drawings by Opper.
Opper, John, 1908-1994
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 7 series:
Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1953-1994 (Box 1; 1 folder)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1948-1994 (Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 3: Personal Business Records, 1960s-1993 (Box 1; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 4: Printed Materials, 1930-2011 (Box 1; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 5: Scrapbook, 1937-2005 ( Box 2; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 6: Artwork, 1963 (Box 2; 1 folder)
Series 7: Photographs, 1926-circa 2011 (Box 3; 0.2 linear feet)
Biographical/Historical note
Chicago born abstract painter and teacher John Opper (1908-1994) moved to New York in the 1930s where he lived and worked for most of his career.
Opper was a founding member of the American Abstract Artist group in 1936, studying with Hans Hofmann the same year. He studied at Cleveland School of Art, Case Western Reserve University, Columbia University and Art Institute of Chicago. Opper received a Guggenheim fellowship in 1969. He was represented by Grace Borgenicht Gallery. He became known for his abstract style that was influenced by both abstract expressionism and color field painting.
Conditions Governing Access note
The John Opper papers are owned by the Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution. Literary rights as possessed by the donor have been dedicated to public use for research, study, and scholarship. The collection is subject to all copyright laws.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Donated by the artist's children, Jane and Joseph Opper, March 27, 2013.
Related Archival Materials note
Oral history interview with John Opper, 1968 September 9-1969 January 3, Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of abstract painter and teacher John Opper measure 1.4 liner feet and are dated 1926 to 2011. The papers contain both professional and personal correspondence, including letters from immediate family. Biographical materials consist of essential data including passports, birth and death certificates, and curriculum vitae. Personal business records relate to the artist's Bowery Street and Amagansett studios, and to art sales through the Grace Borgenicht Gallery. A scrapbook contains newspaper clippings. Additional clippings, group and solo exhibition catalogs and announcements documenting Opper's career, and galley sheets of a children's book illustrated by Opper are included among the printed material. Photographs are of Opper, his family, friends, and paintings. Digital photographs depict the artist and relatives and also include images of genealogical records. The collection also contains a few pen and ink drawings by Opper.
Grace Borgenicht Gallery.; Art--Study and teaching; Artists' studios; Drawings; Painters--New York (State)--New York; Painting, Abstract; Photographs; Scrapbooks
- Biographical Material, 1953-1994; Series 1; 1 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains 5 passports, curricula vitae, New York University faculty identification card, and Opper's death certificate.
  - Biographical Material, 1953-1994 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1948-1995; Series 2; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Correspondence is both professional and personal. Correspondents include immediate family, galleries, and foundations. Also found in this series is the text of a lecture delivered at Rhode Island School of Design in 1981.
  - General Correspondence, circa 1948-1995 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - Letters to Family Members, circa 1950s-1994 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Personal Business Records, 1960s-1993; Series 3; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1
  Studio records concern Opper’s Bowery and Amagansett studios. Inventories are on index cards and in a calendar and include measurements and dates for paintings without a corresponding list of titles.
  - Bowery Studio, 1984-1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Amagansett Studio, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Sales—Grace Borgenicht Gallery, 1991-1993; 1969-1979 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Paintings—Restoration Supplies, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Inventory, 1960s-1985 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Printed Material, 1930-2011; Series 4; 0.5 Linear feet Box 1
  The series include the galley sheets for a children's book illustrated by Opper, newspaper and magazine clippings, exhibition catalogs, and announcements.
  - Roberta E. Lee by Burke Davis, unbound galley sheets, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Printed Material, 1930-2011 (Box 1, Folder 12-24)
- Scrapbook, 1937-2005; Series 5; 0.2 Linear feet Box 2
  This series is comprised of one dismantled scrapbook containing newspaper and magazine clippings about Opper and his artwork.
  - Scrapbook, 1937-2005 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
- Artwork, 1963; Series 6; 1 Folders Box 2
  This series contains sketches by Opper, some loose and others on a printed program from the T.S. "Bremen." All are of people, probably fellow passengers.
  - Sketches, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Photographs, 1926-2011; Series 7; 0.2 Linear feet Box 2
  This series includes photographs, slides, and a DVD of images. Photographs and slides are of Opper and his work.
  - Artwork, 1950s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
  - John Opper, 1930s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - John Opper, Family, and Friends, 1926-1993 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Images of Opper, Artwork, and Relatives; Genealogical Records (1910-1965), 2011; 1 Electronic discs (DVD) (Box 2, Folder 9)
    The disc is incorrectly labeled --it does not include images of Opper with Philip Guston and Franz Kline.